[{"question":"1.An uncertain event or condition that, if it occurs, has a positive or negative effect on a project objectivesis termed.\nA.Random chance\nB.A disaster\nC.Risk\nD.Hazard\nE.Bad luck","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"In the context of projects, risk is an uncertain event or condition that, if it occurs, has a positive or negativeeffect on project objectives.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"2.The chances of a risk event occurring as a project proceeds through its life cycle tends to\nA.Slowly rise\nB.Drop sharply and then level out\nC.Rise sharply and then level out\nD.Remain about the same\nE.Slowly drop","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See Figure 7.1 on Page 212.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"3.The cost impact of a risk event occurring as a project proceeds through its life cycle tends to\nA.Slowly rise\nB.Drop sharply and then level out\nC.Rise sharply and then level out\nD.Remain about the same\nE.Slowly drop","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"The cost impact of a risk event in the project is less if the event occurs earlier rather than later.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"4.The attempt to recognize and manage potential and unforeseen trouble spots that may occur when a project is implementedis known as\nA.Risk forecasting\nB.Risk management\nC.Contingency planning\nD.Scenario analysis\nE.Disaster protection","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"Risk management attempts to recognize and manage potential and unforeseen trouble spots that may occur when theproject is implemented.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"5.Which of the following is not one of the steps in the risk management process?\nA.Risk response development\nB.Risk assessment\nC.Risk identification\nD.Risk tracking\nE.Risk response control","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See Figure 7.2 on Page 213.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"6.The initial step in the risk management process is to\nA.Determine the level of acceptable risk\nB.Assess the risk potential\nC.Identify the risks\nD.Set aside budget funds for managing the risks\nE.Appoint a risk manager","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"See Figure 7.2 on Page 213.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"7.One common mistake made early in the risk identification process is to\nA.Not all possibilities are considered\nB.Participants are over-optimistic\nC.Participants are over-pessimistic\nD.Focus on objectives and not on the events that could produce consequences.\nE.Too much attention is given to past events","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"One common mistake that is made early in the risk identification process is to focus on objectives and not onthe events that could produce consequences.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"8.In the beginning the focus of risk management should be on risks that\nA.Impact the whole project\nB.Impact the critical path\nC.Are known\nD.Have the greatest cost impact\nE.Have the greatest schedule impact","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"The focus at the beginning should be on risks that can affect the whole project as opposed to a specific sectionof the project or network.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"9.The 1999 NASA Mars Climate Orbiter is an example of\nA.Disaster avoidance through proactive risk management\nB.Murphy's Law\nC.Proper use of critical thinking\nD.Mismanaged risk control\nE.Using historical records to assess risk","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"The cost of mismanaged risk control early on in the project is magnified by the ill-fated 1999 NASA Mars ClimateOrbiter.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"10.Which of the following would not be considered a threat?\nA.Inflation\nB.Meeting the project schedule\nC.International disruptions\nD.Economic conditions\nE.Competition","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"There are sources external to the organization, such as inflation, market acceptance, exchange rates, and governmentregulations. In practice, these risk events are often referred to as \"threats\" to differentiate them fromthose that are not within the project manager's or team's responsibility area.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"11.A list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project is termed a risk\nA.Risk profile\nB.Questionnaire\nC.Research\nD.Query\nE.Checklist","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"A risk profile is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"12.Which of the following is typically included in risk profiles?\nA.Management aspects\nB.Market aspects\nC.Technical aspects\nD.Both A and C are included\nE.A, B, and C are all included","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"Risk profiles recognize the unique strengths and weaknesses of the firm; also risk profiles address both technicaland management risks.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"13.All of the following are included in the risk identification process except\nA.Customers\nB.Subcontractors\nC.Competitors\nD.Vendors\nE.None of these are included","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"The risk identification process should not be limited to just the core team. Input from customers, sponsors,subcontractors, vendors, and other stakeholders should be solicited.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"14.One of the keys to success in risk identification is\nA.Critical thinking\nB.Optimism\nC.Pessimism\nD.A \"can do\" attitude\nE.All of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"While a \"can do\" attitude is essential during implementation, project managers have to encourage critical thinkingwhen it comes to risk identification.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"15.The easiest and most commonly used technique for analyzing risks is _____ analysis.\nA.Probability\nB.Scenario\nC.Payback\nD.Risk/reward","type":"fill-in","answer":"B.","help":"Scenario analysis is the easiest and most commonly used technique for analyzing risks.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"16.A risk profile is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project that answersdeveloped from:\nA.When the event might occur in the project\nB.Chances of the event occurring\nC.Interaction with other parts of the project or with other projects\nD.From previous, similar projects\nE.Magnitude or severity of the event's impact\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"17.The risk management tool that is divided into three color-coded zones representing major, moderate, and minorrisks is the riskA.Assessment formB.Responsibility matrixC.Scenario assessmentD.Impact assessmentE.Risk severity matrix","difficulty":"E.Risk severity matrix"},{"question":"The risk severity matrix provides a basis for prioritizing which risks to address. Red zone risks receive firstpriority followed by yellow zone risks. Green zone risks are typically considered inconsequential and ignoredunless their status changes.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"18.The risk assessment form contains all of the following exceptA.Likelihood of the risk event occurringB.Potential impact of the risk eventC.Who will detect the occurrence of the risk event.D.Difficulty of detecting the occurrence of the risk eventE.When the risk event may occur","difficulty":"E.When the risk event may occur"},{"question":"See Figure 7.6 on Page 217.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"19.The two scales of a risk severity matrix measureA.Time, costB.Cost, scheduleC.Impact, costD.Time, impactE.Likelihood, impact","difficulty":"E.Likelihood, impact"},{"question":"The risk matrix presented in Figure 7.7 on page 218 consists of a 5 x 5 array of elements with each element representinga different set of impact and likelihood values.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"20.Which of the following is not one of the probability analysis tools?A.Ratio/range analysisB.Decision treeC.PERT simulationD.PERTE.All of these are probability analysis tools","difficulty":"E.All of these are probability analysis tools"},{"question":"Decision trees have been used to assess alternative courses of action using expected values PERT (program evaluationand review technique) and PERT simulation can be used to review activity and project risk.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"21.This risk assessment tool is a variation of the risk severity matrix that includes the ease of detection foreach of the identified risks.A.PERT simulationB.FMEA analysisC.Ratio/range analysisD.Probability analysisE.Semi-quantitative analysis","difficulty":"E.Semi-quantitative analysis"},{"question":"Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA) extends the risk severity matrix by including ease of detection in theequation: Impact x Probability x Detection = Risk Value.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"22.Which of the following is not included in a Failure Mode and Effects Analysis?A.ImpactB.ProbabilityC.DetectionD.Risk valueE.All of these are included","difficulty":"E.All of these are included"},{"question":"Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA) extends the risk severity matrix by including ease of detection in theequation: Impact x Probability x Detection = Risk Value.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"23.Which of the following is used to review activity and project risk?A.NPVB.S-curvesC.PERTD.Decision treesE.All of these can be used","difficulty":"E.All of these can be used"},{"question":"PERT (program evaluation and review technique) and PERT simulation can be used to review activity and projectrisk.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"24.Which of the following is not one of the potential responses to a specific risk event?A.MitigatingB.RetainingC.IgnoringD.TransferringE.Sharing","difficulty":"E.Sharing"},{"question":"When a risk event is identified and assessed, a decision must be made concerning which response is appropriatefor the specific event. Responses to risk can be classified as mitigating, avoiding, transferring, sharing,or retaining.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"25.A Risk Response Matrix contains all of the following exceptA.Contingency planB.TriggerC.Who is responsible?D.ResponseE.All of these are included in the matrix","difficulty":"E.All of these are included in the matrix"},{"question":"See Figure 7.8 on Page 224.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"26.The demolition of the Seattle Kingdome (Snapshot from Practice) is an example of which of the following?A.MitigatingB.RetainingC.IgnoringD.TransferringE.Sharing","difficulty":"E.Sharing"},{"question":"Reducing risk is usually the first alternative considered. There are basically two strategies for mitigatingrisk: (1) reduce the likelihood that the event will occur and/ or (2) reduce the impact that the adverseevent would have on the project. Most risk teams focus first on reducing the likelihood of risk events since,if successful, this may eliminate the need to consider the potentially costly second strategy. The Dome to\nDust Snapshot from Practice details the steps Controlled Demolition took to minimize damage when they implodedthe Seattle Kingdome.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"27.The risk associated with one of the key members being stuck by lightning would most likely be handled by whichof the following?A.MitigatingB.RetainingC.IgnoringD.TransferringE.Sharing","difficulty":"E.Sharing"},{"question":"The risk of a project manager being struck by lightning at a work site would have major negative impact on theproject, but the likelihood is so low it is not worthy of consideration. Conversely, people do change jobs,so an event like the loss of key project personnel would have not only an adverse impact but also a highlikelihood of occurring in some organizations. If so, then it would be wise for that organization to be proactiveand mitigate this risk by developing incentive schemes for retaining specialists and/or engaging in cross-trainingto reduce the impact of turnover.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"28.Funds that are for identified risks that have a low probability of occurring and that decrease as the projectprogresses are called ______ reserves.A.ManagementB.BudgetC.ContingencyD.PaddedE.Just in case","difficulty":"E.Just in case"},{"question":"Budget reserves are set up to cover identified risks; these reserves are those allocated to specific segmentsor deliverables of the project.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"A.Can often be the kind that cause the project to be shut down.B.ProblematicC.Imposed duration datesD.Both A and B are correctE.A, B, and C are all correct","difficulty":"E.A, B, and C are all correct"},{"question":"Technical risks are problematic; they can often be the kind that cause the project to be shut down.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"30.Detailing all identified risks, including descriptions, category, and probability of occurring, impact, responses,A.Management reservesB.Change controlC.Contingency reservesD.Risk registerE.Risk profiles","difficulty":"E.Risk profiles"},{"question":"A risk register details all identified risks, including descriptions, category, and probability of occurring,impact, responses, contingency plans, owners and current status.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 4: Risk Response ControlLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"31.Which of the following is identified to cover major unforeseen risks and, hence, are applied to the total project?A.Budget reservesB.Management reservesC.Time buffersD.Both B and C are correctE.A, B, and C are all correct","difficulty":"E.A, B, and C are all correct"},{"question":"Management reserve funds are needed to cover major unforeseen risks and, hence, are applied to the total project.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"A.Track all changes that are to be implementedB.Review, evaluates, and approve/disapprove proposed changes formallyC.Identify expected effects of proposed changes on schedule and budgetD.Reflect scope changes in baseline and performance measuresE.All of the above are correct","difficulty":"E.All of the above are correct"},{"question":"See list on page 231.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Change Control ManagementLevel: MediumFill in the Blank Questions","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"33.The ________ impact of a risk event in a project is less if the event occurs earlier rather than later.cost","difficulty":"cost"},{"question":"See Figure 7.1 on Page 212.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"34.The likelihood of a risk event occurring ________ as a project goes through its life cycle.decreases","difficulty":"decreases"},{"question":"See Figure 7.1 on Page 212.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"35.The first step in the Risk Management process is ________.risk identification","difficulty":"risk identification"},{"question":"See Figure 7.2 on Page 213.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"36.Risk events such as inflation, market acceptance, and government regulations are referred to as ________.threats","difficulty":"threats"},{"question":"The sources of project risks are unlimited. There are sources external to the organization, such as inflation,market acceptance, exchange rates, and government regulations. In practice, these risk events are often referredto as \"threats\" to differentiate them from those that are not within the project manager's or team's responsibilityarea.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"37.A ________ is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project.risk profile","difficulty":"risk profile"},{"question":"A risk profile is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"38.The easiest and most commonly used technique for analyzing risks is ________.scenario analysis","difficulty":"scenario analysis"},{"question":"Scenario analysis is the easiest and most commonly used technique for analyzing risks.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"39.The ________ form identifies each risk event, the likelihood of it occurring, the potential impact, when it mayoccur, and the degree of difficulty in detecting it.risk assessment","difficulty":"risk assessment"},{"question":"See Figure 7.6 on Page 217.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"40.The ________ matrix is divided into red, yellow, and green zones representing major, moderate, and minor risks.risk severity","difficulty":"risk severity"},{"question":"The risk severity matrix provides a basis for prioritizing which risks to address. Red zone risks receive firstpriority followed by yellow zone risks. Green zone risks are typically considered inconsequential and ignoredunless their status changes.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"41.The vertical scale on the Risk Severity Matrix measures the _________ of a potential risk event.likelihood","difficulty":"likelihood"},{"question":"See Figure 7.6 on Page 218.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"42.The horizontal scale on the Risk Severity Matrix measures the _________ of a potential risk event.impact","difficulty":"impact"},{"question":"See Figure 7.6 on Page 218.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"43.In __________ the Risk Severity Matrix is extended by including the ease of detecting a risk event occurring.Failure Mote and Effects Analysis (FMEA)","difficulty":"Failure Mote and Effects Analysis (FMEA)"},{"question":"Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA) extends the risk severity matrix by including ease of detection in theequation: Impact x Probability x Detection = Risk Value.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"44.In a ________, three different estimates of activity times are used to statistically predict the time an activitywill take to complete.probability analysis","difficulty":"probability analysis"},{"question":"There are many statistical techniques available to the project manager that can assist in assessing project risk.\nDecision trees have been used to assess alternative courses of action using expected values. Statisticalvariations of net present value (NPV) have been used to assess cash flow risks in projects. Correlationsbetween past projects' cash flow and S-curves (cumulative project cost curve—baseline—over the life of theproject) have been used to assess cash flow risks.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"45.The \"Snapshot from Practice\" case where Ellipsus Systems developed parallel prototype systems (WAP and JAVA)is an example of _________ a risk.avoiding","difficulty":"avoiding"},{"question":"Risk avoidance is changing the project plan to eliminate the risk or condition. Although it is impossible toeliminate all risk events, some specific risks may be avoided before you launch the project. Rikard Kjellberg'ssolution was to have projects in his company's portfolio based on both standards. Ellipsus built early prototypesof both systems and took them to a trade show, with both systems sitting side by side. \"We knew within anhour which way to go,\" says Douglas Davies, the COO. Ellipsus began securing million dollar contracts tosupply its Java-based system to leading U.S. operators.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"46.Testing a new project on a smaller isolated area prior to installing it for the entire organization is an exampleof ________ a risk.mitigating","difficulty":"mitigating"},{"question":"Reducing risk is usually the first alternative considered. There are basically two strategies for mitigatingrisk: (1) reduce the likelihood that the event will occur and/ or (2) reduce the impact that the adverseevent would have on the project. Most risk teams focus first on reducing the likelihood of risk events since,if successful, this may eliminate the need to consider the potentially costly second strategy.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"47.Performance bonds, warranties, and insurance are examples of ________ a risk.transferring","difficulty":"transferring"},{"question":"Passing risk to another party is common; this transfer does not change risk. Passing risk to another party almostalways results in paying a premium for this exemption. Fixed-price contracts are the classic example of transferringrisk from an owner to a contractor.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"48.When the entertainment industry formed a consortium to define a common operating format for DVD it was ________the risk.sharing","difficulty":"sharing"},{"question":"This strategy involves allocating some or all of the ownership of an opportunity to another party who is bestable to capture the opportunity for the benefit of the project. Examples include establishing continuousimprovement incentives for external contractors or joint ventures.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"49.If a risk event is very unlikely to occur the project owner would probably ________ the risk.retain","difficulty":"retain"},{"question":"Some risks are so large it is not feasible to consider transferring or reducing the event (e.g., an earthquakeor flood). The project owner assumes the risk because the chance of such an event occurring is slim.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"50.A ________ identifies what to do if a potential risk event actually occurs.risk response matrix","difficulty":"risk response matrix"},{"question":"See Figure 7.6 on Page 225.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"51.________ reserves are identified for specific work packages and cover risks that have a low probability of occurring.Budget","difficulty":"Budget"},{"question":"These reserves are identified for specific work packages or segments of a project found in the baseline budgetor work breakdown structure. For example, a reserve amount might be added to \"computer coding\" to cover therisk of \"testing\" showing a coding problem. The reserve amount is determined by costing out the acceptedcontingency or recovery plan. The budget reserve should be communicated to the project team.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"52.________ reserves are controlled by the project manager and used to cover major unforeseen risks to the entireproject.Management","difficulty":"Management"},{"question":"These reserve funds are needed to cover major unforeseen risks and, hence, are applied to the total project.For example, a major scope change may appear necessary midway in the project.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"53.A ____________ is an alternative that will be used if a possible foreseen risk event becomes a reality.contingency plan","difficulty":"contingency plan"},{"question":"A contingency plan is an alternative plan that will be used if a possible foreseen risk event becomes a reality.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"54.A ____________ is useful for summarizing how the project team plans to manage risks that have been identified.Risk Response Matrix","difficulty":"Risk Response Matrix"},{"question":"Risk response matrices such as the one shown in Figure 7.8 on page 225 are useful for summarizing how the projectteam plans to manage risks that have been identified.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency PlanningLevel: EasyTrue / False Questions","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"55.The probability that a risk event will occur is higher during the initial stages of a project.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"The chances of a risk event occurring (e.g., an error in time estimates, cost estimates, or design technology)are greatest in the concept, planning, and start-up phases of the project.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"56.Due to the impact over a long period of time, risk events that occur in the early stages of a project will havea greater cost impact than those that occur in later stages.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"The cost impact of a risk event in the project is less if the event occurs earlier rather than later.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"57.During risk identification the smaller risks should be identified first because they will naturally lead to identifyingthe larger risks.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"The focus at the beginning should be on risks that can affect the whole project as opposed to a specific sectionof the project or network.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"58.One common mistake that is made early on in the risk identification process is to focus on consequences and noton the events that could produce consequences.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"One common mistake that is made early in the risk identification process is to focus on objectives and not onthe events that could produce consequences.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"59.Risks such as inflation and monetary exchange rates are not usually included in a project's risk assessment.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"The sources of project risks are unlimited. There are sources external to the organization, such as inflation,market acceptance, exchange rates, and government regulations. In practice, these risk events are often referredto as \"threats\" to differentiate them from those that are not within the project manager's or team's responsibilityarea.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"60.The first step in the risk management process is Risk Assessment.Refer to Figure 7.2FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"See Figure 7.2 on Page 213. The first step is Risk Identification. Risk Assessment is the second step.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"61.A risk profile is a list of questions that have been developed and refined from previous, similar projects.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"A risk profile is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project. These questionshave been developed and refined from previous, similar projects.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"62.The risk identification process should be limited to just the core project team.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"The risk identification process should not be limited to just the core team. Input from customers, sponsors,subcontractors, vendors, and other stakeholders should be solicited.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"63.Since the goal is to find problems before they happen, the project manager should encourage critical thinkingwhen it comes to risk identification.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"One of the keys to success in risk identification is attitude. While a \"can do\" attitude is essential duringimplementation, project managers have to encourage critical thinking when it comes to risk identification.The goal is to find potential problems before they happen.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"64.The Risk Severity Matrix rates risk events based upon schedule and cost.Refer to Figure 7.7FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"See Figure 7.7 on Page 218. The Risk Severity Matrix events are based on likelihood and impact.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"65.In a Risk Severity Matrix a green zone risk is considered inconsequential and ignored unless their status changes.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"The risk severity matrix Green zone risks are typically considered inconsequential and ignored unless their statuschanges.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"66.The quality and credibility of the risk analysis process requires that different levels of risk probabilitiesand impacts be defined.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"The quality and credibility of the risk analysis process requires that different levels of risk probabilitiesand impacts be defined.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"67.Adopting proven technology instead of experimental technology is an example of mitigating a risk.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"Adopting proven technology instead of experimental technology is an example of avoiding risk.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"68.The FMEA method calculates a risk value by assigning ease of detection ratings to the key risk elements.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (FMEA) extends the risk severity matrix by including ease of detection in theequation: Impact x Probability x Detection = Risk Value.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"69.Performance bonds, warranties, and guarantees are financial instruments used to share risk.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"Performance bonds, warranties, and guarantees are other financial instruments used to transfer risk.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"70.Fixed price contracts are an example of transferring risk from an owner to a contractor.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Fixed-price contracts are the classic example of transferring risk from an owner to a contractor.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"71.Scheduling outdoor work in the summer, investing in up front safety training, and choosing high quality materialsare examples of retaining a risk.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"An example of reducing the probability of risks occurring are scheduling outdoor work during the summer months,investing in up-front safety training, and choosing high-quality materials and equipment.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"72.Budget reserves are setup to cover identified risks associated with specific segments of a project while managementreserves are set up to cover unidentified risks associated with the total project.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Budget reserves are set up to cover identified risks; these reserves are those allocated to specific segmentsor deliverables of the project. Management reserves are set up to cover unidentified risks and are allocatedto risks associated with the total project.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"73.Change management systems involve reporting, controlling, and recording changes to the project baseline.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Change management systems involve reporting, controlling, and recording changes to the project baseline. (Note:Some organizations consider change control systems part of configuration management.)\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Change Control ManagementLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"74.Project managers need to establish an environment in which participants feel comfortable raising concerns andadmitting mistakes.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"Project managers need to establish an environment in which participants feel comfortable raising concerns andadmitting mistakes.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Constructing a Project NetworkLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"75.Contingency funding is made up of budget reserves and management reserves.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"In practice, the contingency reserve fund is typically divided into budget and management reserve funds for controlpurposes.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: EasyShort Answer Questions","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"76.Describe the relationship between the likelihood of a risk event occurring and the cost of fixing the risk eventas a project proceeds through its life cycle.","difficulty":"as a project proceeds through its life cycle."},{"question":"In the early stages of the project life cycle the probability of a risk event occurring is greater than at anyother time and the cost to fix it is lower than at any other point. As time passes the probability of occurrencedrops lower and lower while the cost rises. See figure 7-1.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Risk Management ProcessLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"77.Identify and briefly describe the four steps in risk management.","difficulty":"77.Identify and briefly describe the four steps in risk management."},{"question":"1. Risk Identification; all possible risks are identified, 2. Risk Assessment; risks are assessed in terms ofimportance and need for attention, 3. Risk Response Development; plans are developed to respond if the riskactually occurs, and 4. Risk Response Control; the actual response to the risk and controlling changes associatedwith the risks.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"78.Describe the process for identifying project risks.","difficulty":"78.Describe the process for identifying project risks."},{"question":"The project manager pulls together a risk management team consisting of core team members and other relevantstakeholders and uses brainstorming and other techniques to identify project risks. Focus should be on theWBS and the risks associated with the deliverables.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"79.What is a risk profile and what benefits does it provide to risk management?","difficulty":" and what benefits does it provide to risk management?"},{"question":"A risk profile is a list of questions that address traditional areas of uncertainty on a project. The questionshave been developed and refined from previous, similar projects. These profiles are generated and maintainedby the project office and are updated and refined during the life of the project. This historical file assistsin identifying risks for future projects.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"80.Identify at least six items that may be included on a Risk Profile.","difficulty":"80.Identify at least six items that may be included on a Risk Profile."},{"question":"1. technical requirements, 2. Design, 3. Testing, 4. Development, 5. Schedule, 6. Budget, 7. Quality, 8. Management,9. Work Environment, 10. Staffing, 11. Customer, and 12. Contractors.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Step 1: Risk IdentificationLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"81.How should a risk assessment be conducted?","difficulty":" be conducted?"},{"question":"Not all identified risks deserve attention, some are trivial and others are serious threats. The Scenario analysisis the easiest and most commonly used technique for analyzing risks. Each risk is assessed in terms of 1.what the risk are, 2. the outcomes of the event's occurrence, 3. the severity of the event's impact, 4. theprobability of the event occurring, 5. when the event may occur, and 6. the interaction with other partsof the project or other projects.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"82.What is a Risk Severity Matrix and what does it do?","difficulty":" and what does it do?"},{"question":"Risks are placed on a matrix that has Likelihood as the vertical axis and Impact as the horizontal axis. Risksin the upper right corner are considered major, those further left are considered moderate, while the restare considered minor. The matrix is usually color-coded with the major risks in red, moderate risks in yellowand minor risks in green. It is an easily read graphical representation of a project's risks.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Step 2: Risk AssessmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"83.Identify and briefly describe the five ways to respond to identified risks.","difficulty":"83.Identify and briefly describe the five ways to respond to identified risks."},{"question":"1. Mitigate the risk; duplicate systems, backup systems, alternate technology development, 2. Avoid the risk;changing the project plan to eliminate the risk, 3. Transfer the risk; fixed-price contract, insurance, 4.Sharing the risk; find others to share the costs of the risk, and 5. Retain the risk; take preventative measuresto reduce the risk such as training.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"84.What is the difference between budget reserves and management reserves?","difficulty":"?"},{"question":"Budget reserves are controlled by team participants and have been identified for known risks that have a lowchance of occurring and are directly associated with specific work packages. Management reserves are controlledby the project manager and cover items which were unforeseen usually at the total project level.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"85.What is Change Control Management and what function does it perform?","difficulty":"85.What is Change Control Management and what function does it perform?"},{"question":"Change Control Management is the formal process for making and tracking changes once a project has started. Anychanges must be detailed and accepted by the project team. Risks associated with making changes are thusassessed and documented.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Change Control ManagementLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"86.Identify and briefly describe the parts of a Risk Response Matrix and explain how one would be used.","difficulty":"86.Identify and briefly describe the parts of a Risk Response Matrix and explain how one would be used."},{"question":"The parts are: the risk event, the response, contingency plan, trigger, and who is responsible. It is used forsummarizing how the project team plans to manage risks that have been identified.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Step 3: Risk Response DevelopmentLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"87.Compare and contrast budget reserves and management reserves.","difficulty":"87.Compare and contrast budget reserves and management reserves."},{"question":"Budget reserves are for known risks associated with specific work packages and controlled by the project managers.Management reserves are for unforeseen risks associated with the overall project and are controlled by uppermanagement.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Contingency Funding and Time BuffersLevel: Difficult7-1","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"","difficulty":""}]